A Guide to the New Jersey Zinc Corporation (Austinville, VA) Records II, 1925-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
New Jersey Zinc Corporation (Austinville, VA) Records II, 1925-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-037
3.3 cu. ft. 6 boxes
The New Jersey Zinc Corporation Records II contain maps, surveys, memoranda, and reports.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections in 1999.
Historical Note
The lead mines of southwest Virginia were first discovered by Colonel John Chiswell in 1756. Chiswell mined lead ore on the New River in Augusta County (now Wythe County) from 1760 to 1766, and furnished large supplies of lead to Virginia during the French and Indian War. A fort and trading post were sut up at this time near the mines. Chiswell died in 1766, and ownership of the mines was trasnferred to William Byrd. The mines were leased to the state during the Revolutionary War.
In 1789 Moses and Stephen Austin contacted for the lead mines and bought them from the Commonwealth of Virginia. Due to mismanagement, the lead mines reverted back to the state in 1802. In 1806, Thomas Jackson bought the proerty, now in the town of Austinville, in Wythe County, at a public auction in Richmond. He constructed a shot-tower on the New River, which operated from 1812 to 1830 and still stands today.
From 1830 to 1898, the property was mined by Daniel Sheffey and David Pierce or their descendants. From 1838 to the 1850s, the firm was called the Wythe Lead Mines Company. The Union Lead Mine Company, as it was called in 1860, contributed more than 2,000 tons of lead to Confederate troops in the Civil War. After the discovery of zinc in the 1860s, the Union Lead Company formed the Wythe Lead and Zinc Company.
The Wythe Lead and Zinc Company sold all of its ore in 1898 to the Bertha Mineral Company, which operated in Pulaski, six miles northeast of Austinville. In 1902, the New Jersey Zinc Corporation purchased Bertha holdings and the Austinville property.
For more information on the early history of the Austinville lead and zinc mines, see: Austin, Vera Lee. 1977. The Southwest Virginia Lead Works, 1756-1802. Thesis (M.A.)--Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1977.
Scope and Content
The New Jersey Zinc Corporation Records contain maps, surveys, memoranda, and reports by and about the company. Maps and surveys range from the mines in Georgia, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia and often relate the mineral deposits found there. The collection also houses weekly reports that detail the accomplishments of the week and worker hours. The General Instruction Memorandums show how the New Jersey Zinc Company complied with federal regulation and how the owners in New York shared this information with their supervisors and workers in the mine areas.
Arrangement
The collection in arranged in chronological order, with the exception of two binders of material and oversized maps and surveys, which appear at the end of the collection, each in their own separate boxes.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Special Collections contains another collection related to the New Jersey Zinc Corporation. See New Jersey Zinc Corporation [Austinville, Virginia] Records. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database. Ms1991-032.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
New Jersey Zinc Corporation.
Local Subjects:
Local/Regional History
Contents List
- Titanium Bearing Lands Near Elf, NC, 1925 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Articles and Publications, 1926-1965 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Applied Potential Survey, 1949 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Geology of the Kennesaw Mtn - Sweat Mtn Area of Cobb County, GA, 1951 (Box-folder 1-4 to 1-6 (3 folders))
- Monthly Reports, August-December 1951 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Geologic Maps of Georgia, 1952 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Reconnaissance Geologic Survey of the South Paulding County Area, GA, 1952 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Thin Section List, 1952-55 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Exploration of the Little Bob Mine Area, GA, 1953 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Exploration of the Swift Prospect, GA, 1953 (Box-folder 2-3)
- General Instruction Memorandums, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Geochemical Prospecting in the Fall Branch Belt of Knox Dolamite, TN, 1953 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Maps of Mineral, VA, with Indexes, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 2-6)
- Weekly Reports, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 2-7 to 2-8; 3-1 (3 folders))
- Work Progress Summaries, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Lithium Potential, Kings Mountain Pegmatite Belt, NC, 1954 (Box-folder 3-3)
- Operation of Radioactivity Surveys in NC, 1955 (Box-folder 3-4)
- Preliminary Report of Metallic Mineral Deposits of Charlotte, Greensboro, and Raleigh, NC, 1956 (Box-folder 3-5 to 3-6 (2 folders))
- Inter-office Correspondence and Maps, 1969 (Box-folder 3-7)
- Soil Sample Location Maps, 1969 (Box-folder 3-8)
- Geochemical Sample Record, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
- Geology Lab Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
- Drilling, 1926-1955 (Box 4)
- Geophysics: Geochemical Prospect, Methods and Equipment, Soils, 1926-1955 (Box 5)
- Oversize Surveys and Maps, 1949-1964 (Box 6)